Finding aid to the Brigitte Jordan papers SSC.MS.00634
Sophia Smith Collection
Brigitte Jordan papers
1975-2015
Sophia Smith Collection
Irwin, Robert
SSC.MS.00634
20.5 linear feet (15 record cartons, 4 legal size document boxes)
0.9 Gigabytes (1,048 files: digital images, video, and documents)
In the 1970s, Brigitte Jordan conducted seminal work in the study of cross-cultural birth practices, including home birth and hospital birth, in the Yucatan and in Holland, Sweden and the United States, resulting in publication of the book Birth in Four Cultures (1983). She taught and conducted research for many years at the university level, where her interests focused on the dynamics of change in the medical systems of developing countries. Her papers consist of audiovisual materials, images, publications, presentations, and research files for an anthropological study conducted by Jordan, of cross-cultural childbirth practices in Mexico, Holland, Sweden, and the U.S., circa 1970s, published in her book Birth in Four Cultures (1983). Included are videotapes of hospital and home births and verbatim transcriptions in Spanish, Dutch, Swedish, with English translations. Of special interest are films of indigenous midwifery practices, including several births Jordan attended as apprentice to a village midwife in the Yucatan. Also included are a series of pen and ink drawings of a Mexican midwife attending a pregnant women, field notes and other research materials.
Biographical Note
Brigitte Jordan conducted seminal work in the study of cross-cultural birth practices in the 1970s, including home birth and hospital birth, in the Yucatan and in Holland, Sweden and the United States, resulting in publication of the book Birth in Four Cultures (1983). She taught and conducted research for many years at the university level, where her interests focused on the dynamics of change in the medical systems of developing countries. In 1988, Jordan began working as a corporate anthropologist, and her research and consulting interests evolved to include the changing nature of work under the impact of new communication and information technologies and the consequent transformation of ways of life, societal institutions, and global economies. A sought-after speaker and leader of executive workshops, Jordan was the author of many scholarly and technical publications. Brigitte (Gitti) Muller Jordan was born in Passau, Germany, in 1937 and grew up there during World War II. Her parents were Gertrude Frank Muller, who died in 1944 when Jordan was seven, and Josef Karl Muller. She married Richard Jordan in 1958, and theyt had three children: Wayne (b. 1959), Susan (b. 1960), and Kimsey (b. 1961); the couple divorced in 1968. Jordan earned her B.A. and M.A. degrees in Anthropology at California State University at Sacramento, and her Ph.D. in Social Science/Anthropology from University of California at Irvine in 1975. She died at home on May 24, 2016 of pancreatic cancer. Her website states, "she chose to meet the cancer on her own terms, refusing medical intervention, embracing hospice care, and remaining as physically and mentally active as humanly possible until the end."
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Accruals
This collection is comprised of the following accessions, some of which may not have accession records. Accession numbers: 08S-107, 2018-S-0027. Accessions were received on the following dates: 2008-12-01, 2018-05-24.
Existence and Location of Copies
Video tapes may be reproductions of original films.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The a/v materials look fine but the paper documents have extensive water damage, including mold. The materials in Boxes 6-9 have been minimally stabilised by drying them out and refoldering them, but everything should be photocopied asap.
Scope and Contents
The Brigitte Jordon papers consist of audiovisual materials, images, publications, presentations, and research files for an anthropological study, conducted by Jordan, of cross-cultural childbirth practices in Mexico, Holland, Sweden, and the U.S., circa 1970s, published in her book Birth in Four Cultures (1983). Included are videotapes of hospital and home births; and verbatim transcriptions in Spanish, Dutch, Swedish, with English translations. Of special interest are films of indigenous midwifery practices, including several births Jordan attended as apprentice to a village midwife in the Yucatan. Also included are a series of pen and ink drawings of a Mexican midwife attending a pregnant women, field notes and other research materials. Most recent accession includes materials from her work in Palo Alto with the XEROX Corporation at the Palo Alto Research Center, teaching materials from her anthropology classes, and numerous materials from workplace ethnography studies conducted by Jordan.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form, as well as digitized materials, that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
General
Brigitte Jodon died in 2016. This collection was closed during her lifetime; no processing was permitted during her liufetime. Papers from earlier collections are as of yet unprocessed.
Childbirth -- Cross-cultural studies; Childbirth -- Mexico -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Childbirth at home -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Childbirth -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Midwives -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Obstetrics -- Social aspects; Jordan, Brigitte. Birth in four cultures: a crosscultural investigation of childbirth in Yucatan, Holland, Sweden, and the United States -- Sources; Notes; Videotapes; Research; Logbooks; Transcripts; Drawings; Computer media; Jordan, Brigitte; Irwin, Robert; Jordan, Brigitte
- Brigitte Jordan papers 2018-S-0027, 2018-S-0027; Irwin, Robert; Jordan, Brigitte; 11.75 linear feet (9 record cartons and 1 legal document box); 7 items (3 floppy disks and 4 CDs); 0.9 Gigabytes (1,048 files: digital images, video, and documents)
  Scope and Contents
  Papers consist of audiovisual materials, images, presentations and research files for an anthropological study, conducted by Jordan, of cross-cultural childbirth practices in Mexico, Holland, Sweden, and the U.S., circa 1970s, published in her book Birth in Four Cultures (1983). This accession also includes materials from her work in Palo Alto with the XEROX at the Palo Alto Research Center, teaching materials from her anthropology classes, and numerous materials from workplace ethnography studies conducted by Jordan.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Held by Jordan's widower, Robert Irwin, after her death and transferred to Smith College by him.
  Videotapes; DVD video discs; Audiocassettes; CDs; Floppy disks; Irwin, Robert
  - RepTool papers (patent, business plan, IRL agreement, assessments, billing), 1996-1998; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - Xerox papers (work practices, research, ISL workshop), 1991-2008; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Consulting papers, various companies (Pentalog, Texaco, Prudential, IBM), 1995-2001; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Society for Applied Anthropology (SfAA) conference materials, 1991-2011 (Box 1)
  - Talegen papers, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Intuit papers, 2006-2010; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Papers for various workshops (PARC, DSTO), 1995-1999; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Workplace Project: airline operations, 1989-1990; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fujitsu workplace study, 2004-2009; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Human organization (HO) and distributed work groups (DWG) papers, 2004-2007; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Microsoft Mauna Kea project, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Writing group papers and article outlines, 1995-2008; 8 folders (8 folder) (Box 2)
  - Teaching material for Anthropology 380 at Michigan State University, 1978-1986; 16 folders (16 folders) (Box 3)
  - "Double Helix" project papers, photos, and research, 2007-2015; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Corporate ethnography book drafts, email correspondence, and reviews, 2009-2012; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Communication delay study papers, 1996-1997; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Interaction Analysis Lab papers and publications, 2001-2002; 5 items (1 folder and 4 books) (Box 4)
  - Intel papers (data files, slides, tape transcripts, documents), 2003-2006; 6 folders (6 folder) (Box 4)
  - Workplace ethnography articles, 1986-2007; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - Lifescapes manuscripts and working material, 2000-2001; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Workplace ethnography workshop materials (Austria, PDC, Statoil, San Pedro), 1995-2010; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - Monsanto papers (S1, S2, Frontiers of Leadership, miscellany), 1997-1998; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - Brigitte Jordan personal papers (CV, published works lists, interviews, media appearances, awards, recommendations, correspondence), 1976-1994; 12 folders (12 folders) (Box 5)
  - Photos from various field studies, 1994-2001; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Institute for Research on Learning (IRL) papers, publications, and photos, 1994-1999; 10 folders (10 folders); 23 items (23 booklets) (Box 6)
  - Palo Alto Research Center (PARC) papers and projects, 1984-2011; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - XBS papers (presentations, correspondence, project files), 1992-1998; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Obstetrical anthropology articles by Brigitte Jordan, 1977-1989; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Anthropological articles on various topics (healthcare, computerization, knowledge), 1986-1997; 7 folders (7 folder) (Box 7)
  - "Birth in Four Cultures" correspondence, reviews, advertising, 1987-1993; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Sacramento State and UCI papers by Brigitte Jordan, 1965-1974; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Photograph slides from the Yucatan, advertising, 1991-1997; 3 boxes (3 boxes of slides); 3 folders (3 binders of slides) (Box 8)
  - Photograph slides from the Yucatan, Xerox, IRL/IAL, airport workplace ethnography, 1990-1998; 9 folders (7 binders and 2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Video cassettes: "Studies in Human Birth, Yucatan, Mexico" 1-3, ECV and copy, 1987; 5 items (5 tapes) (Box 10)
  - Audio cassettes: IAL, conferences, personal, travel, 1972-1998; 26 items (26 tapes) (Box 10)
  - Brigitte Jordan electronic records, images and video
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
    Brigette Jordan's electronic files consist primarily of digital images, and few small videos, labelled "Peneng pix," from 2003. Also includes are articles and other documents related to her research and consulting work, dated 1993-99. For more information see the detailed file list.
    - Papers, and other documents, 1993-1999; 2 items 2 floppy discs (Word documents) (Box 10)
    - Brazil paper, 1 items (1 compact disc) (Box 10)
      CD01 contains QuarkXPress file (desktop publishing document), which requires QuarkXPress, or Adobe InDesign wih Q2ID plugin, to read. There are also images on disc.
    - Penang pix: digital images and video, 2003 December 05; 2 items (2 compact discs) (Box 10)
      The compact discs in this file have been copied to networked storage by Special Collections staff for preservation and access. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content. Note: CD01 contains a QuarkXPress file (desktop publishing document) which requires QuarkXPress, or Adobe InDesign wih Q2ID plugin, to read. The remaining files are digital images and video.
    - Brigitte Jordan presenting: digital images, 2001; 1 items (1 compact disc) (Box 10)
- Brigitte Jordan website: "Lifescapes", First captured June 13, 2018; 1 website (single)
  The archived website of Brigitte Jordan (http://www.lifescapes.org/) was first captured in 2016 and subsequent periodic captures are scheduled. The site includes biographical information, a bibliography, full text of her papers, information about workshops and speaking engagements.